now we now introduce the core algorith
for this uh section this lecture which
is uh the base filter and I'm going to
write the algorith in a form of a kind
of a python function um the uh algorith
is um going is um this the
base let's say underscore filter it has
uh three arguments the first argument is
the
belief of where we are we in the
previous time instance St minus one and
this is EV you know evidently the
posterior uh belief or posterior
probability of what we are in the
previous state um so what what was our
previous state was and then the other
one argument is this action that we take
at this point in time T and the
measurement ZT okay so these are the
three
arguments and uh there is a kind of a
for Loop uh we expect to see a for Loop
because as we said the discussion the
the algorith is um going to be
recursive so for all STS for all the
states
STS uh first we are
estimating the belief hatut of that
state
uh because we are going
to uh execute an
action and uh for that action that we
are
executing we are uh effectively going to
uh create a posterior that we will
effectively
integrate uh the um all the
possibilities almost like the
convolution or some
rule okay so let's let me write it down
this is St given St minus one this is my
uh transitional model if you remember
from
earlier and uh this is the belief of St
minus one this is the incoming
belief where I believe I was uh before
and I use where sometimes in this
discussion because in the back of my
mind sometimes I have this simple
localization kind of uh uh sort of use
case but please replace the wear with uh
what was my previous state and okay so
uh that is uh uh basically the first
Formula we'll actually draw it a little
bit to see exactly what is what is going
going on a bit later and then the second
part the second part of the algorith is
now that I have the belief had I will do
the so-called uh measurement
update uh this is also known as um
prediction prediction
step and this is
the uh
measurement update step the prediction
step is kind of blind we are not
considering any measurement and uh as we
are just taking the action and then the
second step involves the measurement
update so it's a normalizing constant
times p
of ZT given
St times the belief
cut of St which we calculated over here
and then after we ex exceed this kind of
for
Loop uh we are
returning the belief uh of uh let me
write it as a return statement
the belief of STD which also worth
mentioning how similar uh because it's
exactly what what's happening this uh
line two line is to with the two
probability rules that we have looked at
the probability review uh video so this
one is um very uh similar to the sum
Rule and I'll write the sum rule in a
moment and the this one is similar to
the product
rule and we'll see how this is also uh
obviously the product rule is
associating itself with the very
definition of the base Rule and that's
why we took the name of base filter and
filter is a kind of a term that we have
used extensively in electrical
engineering to denote um to to to
actually call functions that are going
to be receiving if you like a stream and
uh are are doing exactly the same job
over and over again okay so this is uh
basically what's happening over there uh
so this function will be called now now
that we have the
belief s of T in the next iteration uh
this belief of s will actually go here
another action will be taken and and a
measurement will be received and then
the whole thing will repeat over and
over again that's the kind of recursive
step but coming back to these kind of
two lines
uh the one and let's me call it one and
two uh the line one the
prediction uh
step is
related to uh the sum rule or the
marginalization if you like Rule and if
you remember the marginalization rule
was uh uh P of x uh let let me call this
P of X I think I used I think X and Y
variables when I was discussing these
two uh probability foundational
probability rules so I said P of X is
the sum over all y's of P of X comma
y or now that I can use also the product
rule over there to expand this joint is
is
p of um
x given y * P of Y so replace the Y with
the
state no matter the index and replace uh
X uh with the I think you can replace a
state with a
belief uh on T minus one and this one
with the uh State St okay so uh then
effectively you have what we have in uh
in equation one over here okay so this
is the prediction step um is related is
related to the sum
rule okay and then the other uh comment
is the um that the uh measurement update
uh is um related to the product rule uh
and to the base rule as follows we know
that the U product rule was uh the very
much the uh P of X comma Y is equal to P
of x given y * P of Y we also know that
P of Y given comma X is equal to P of Y
given x uh time P of
X and so from these two given the fact
that P of X comma Y is equal to P of Y
given an
x uh we can actually
conclude the very important kind of
relationship that gives us
the so-called posterior probability P of
Y given
x uh is equal to P of x given y times
the probability of Y which is called
likelihood times the prior / P of X and
actually we can write that as
EA where ITA is associated with the
normalizing a factor 1 / P of X which is
sometimes very difficult to to estimate
and but in this case we will see that
it's kind of a straightforward for the
case of uh the case of we will do in um
it has to do with a discrete version of
this base filter which is the first
implementation we'll see in a moment
times a p of Y uh sorry of x given
y time P of Y so here you actually can
see that instead of X in this case we
have the me measurement z uh let me
write it instead of Z the
measurement and instead of why we have
the
state um and uh so this is basically
what we have um in this U kind of
association between uh going uh from uh
the first step and the second step to
another recursion to to update
and find the next uh version of the
state in the next time instant now
obviously we need to see some kind of
visualization of what's really happen to
see why this kind of makes sense and
we'll have plenty of those and some kind
of a python notebooks in the simple
single dimensional case to see what is
happening uh but in the broad uh broad
terms uh let's say that I am uh in a
room and I'm using now the localization
kind of use case
let's assume that I have some kind of
um uh furniture furniture which I'm kind
of aware of U it's uh coordinates and I
have if you like a robot and let's say
that is located right here in this in
this cell and makes a
move
um the moment that the robot makes a
move its location without any
measurement
information uh can be
represented by some kind of probability
distribution okay which is the posterior
probability distribution that is my uh
belief
C the moment I I take an action uh so
this thing is was induced this
transition was induced by this kind of
action uh and that gave raise to the
belief C obviously I have some kind of
estimate uh of some belief
uh for uh let's say the
St uh minus one I have um this is my
belief of
St uh so a transition from St minus one
to St and as we will see the
uncertainty um about the uh New State uh
is um growing uh in the absence of any
measurement and then uh what I do is
um uh the measurement is actually coming
in uh indicating let's say some
measurement that kind of indicates how
in a proximity kind of sensor how close
is this kind of new uh location with
respect to this uh object and what will
actually happen in the second kind of
Step the uncertainty uh there will be
some
correction and uh maybe that correction
will uh uh you know be like this so this
will be my my belief of
St and this correction as we will see
reduces the uncertainty uh associated
with the new state so we are uh every
time we are moving blind as you can
intuitively understand in an environment
we are expanding in terms of my
covariance of error uh that I see about
my state represented by this kind of
byar Contour diagram of this byar let's
say gausian um and then every time that
I have have a measurement uh which I now
do the correction step the measurement
update kind of Step that conv variance
uh sort of reduces and the intuition
behind it is that now that I have um
that additional kind of variable uh what
can I say uh more about that kind of
posterior okay and definitely that kind
of will reduce uh the
um the uncertainty about my state which
in this case is a localization use case
so that is the you know whole story of
what we will see how this kind of filter
operates and uh we will see now that uh
very clearly in the single dimensional
case so what we will do now next we will
uh first address two cases one is the
discrete case uh and uh in the discrete
case we will see a robot uh trying to
perform that kind of base filter um and
then we will address The Continuous case
uh and this in the continuous case we
will be uh looking at gausian
distributions to uh help us quantify the
operation in uh in in that kind of space