we should imagine these uh networks that
we call fully connected Network
architectures to
resemble uh some form of a pyramidal
shape I call it like
this uh okay so we have here at the
bottom of this pyramid is the input
X okay this pencil is all right we have
this x which is is fitting the input um
and we'll call this the so-called input
layer and we will have
stacks of additional layers one uh one
on top of the other so in general we'll
have layer
l l+ one L +2 all the way to the last
layer that we call as we said the
head and uh this input layer now I'm not
going to I'm going to just use the these
circles to represent the neurons this
input is going to be
fed to all the
neurons and each
neuron is going to
be connected to all of the
neurons of the layer above it and so on
and so on so I'm not going to draw all
the lines because it will be a fairly
messy kind of Di diagram and uh okay
maybe I drew too
many
layers let me call this now the
head it's now easy to see what's
happening and evidently over here we're
going to have the white hat that's now
my head
and this whole thing is going to
be the
body all right so that's uh that is uh
if you like
the um canonical kind of architecture we
will see for fully connected kind of
networks now each of obviously we cannot
really go on with drawing as we have
been doing up to now so we have to
Define if you like a mathematical AB
ruction of each layer so I will just
going to draw how we will represent one
layer that we'll be calling the dense
layer or fully connected layer but is
typically also known as dense because
there's a dense connectivity
diagram uh and a dense Matrix which is
going to be representing this
connectivity so let me just draw
the uh layer I'm going to use this kind
of a trapezoidal
symbol to
indicate uh this
uh Matrix Now by Vector
that's let's say the L
layer matrix by Vector now since I I put
X there it's better to just put an index
of one there because that's basically
the first
layer followed by this kind of a bias
and followed by a new nonlinear function
that we call the
ru now it makes sense this kind of block
diagram we see in front of us so forget
a little bit about this kind of a new
nonlinear function which we call
rectified linear unit uh but uh just
kind of stay here in this kind of
portion so we actually see that we take
this x vector and this x Vector let's
call this to be um has dimensionality of
n x let's write this down so X is
belongs to R to the^ of NX in other
words x the number of dimensions of of X
is NX *
1 and typically by a matrix by Vector
multiplication we are able to do some
form of dimensionality reduction as you
can see the canonical shape of this kind
of network is to per perform subsequent
projections from one layer to another
down to a potentially a single scale
scalar this scalar unit is the
interpreted evidently as the probability
of the positive class given the input X
as we have seen in the case of
classification or could be uh the U uh
the real number in the case of
regression okay but that's really the
limit so we can start with some really
large dimensional uh Vector X and highly
dimensional Vector X and actually
conclude into this into a scaler so how
we will actually do that well it all we
need to do is to Dimension properly the
W Matrix so each layer is doing its own
kind of dimensionality uh reduction uh
right here at this point so our W Matrix
is going to uh be such that it will need
to we start from some uh desired Z that
we want to form so the Z is given by W X
plus b WX +
B so that is my uh operation up to this
point in time uh so if we are to
form uh some NZ * 1
Vector where NZ is going to be uh much
uh smaller uh than the n n x all we need
to do is to make sure that we Dimension
the
W so let's say NZ time NX that's the
dimensionals of
W uh because it's a right hand sign
multiplication some authors also treat
it as a left hand side it's one and the
same
thing plus the bias which is NZ *
1 so this multiplication now makes sense
uh that it will produce uh the uh NZ
Dimensions at the output uh and uh we
can just make sure that we have NZ less
than NX again it's up to us to Define
exactly what type of Dimensions we need
each layer to produce and to reduce
effectively now in terms of the other
thing that we have actually written over
here empirically has been shown that and
this is something that we will
understand after we treat back
propagation empirically has been shown
that a new uh nonlinear
unit that I am going to plot over
here this nonlinear unit that we call
the reu is called rectified linear unit
it is linear unit for all positive value
so that's this angle is
45° uh 45° and then we have
U the input Z and the output this axis
is Ru of
Z and uh the all
negative logits Z are mapped to zero and
that's what makes it nonlinear if you
have minus one it's zero if you have one
minus one million it's also zero okay so
um the um reu from now on we will write
it as a an expression which
effectively agrees with this diagram R
of Z is is equal to Max of 0 comma Z
that is the
equation um when Z is positive uh the
output is
z if it is negative the output will be
zero that's that's how this equation is
should be read and uh basically we are
done we have now one uh dense
layer the block diagram of a dense layer
and what we will do is we'll now see um
an example of
um where we actually going to be put all
these kind of multiple layers uh stacked
together so that is called the
dense
layer and so let's now uh move into into
this example and see what
happens an example application that
we're going to see is the so-called
multiclass classification
and for that uh application we'll be
using a notebook that is in our site
called the shold fashionist case
study uh the um notebook can be launched
in Google collab with a single button so
as you scroll this you will uh basically
press this button to go to
collab uh which is an environment of
python runtime uh that uh is in the
cloud and is offering to us also some
accelerated kind of compute for all our
applications here so you can uh for that
specific example it's actually a good
idea to change the runtime type to uh
that of uh
GPU and you can select the cheapest kind
of GPU it's the T T4 in this specific um
uh case uh and uh if you are uh to you
know pay a subscription to Google then
you can select some more powerful GP but
for our application here uh that that
GPU is sufficient okay so you can press
the save button over here and what is um
now happening is that you can uh connect
to Google cloud and the Google Cloud
will actually give you uh a computation
Resource as you can see here with some
memories and CPU and and and the T4 GPU
to be able to run uh this application so
um I hope everyone is familiar with py
py notebooks and if not we have other
videos that actually can of teach you
the
basics uh but this application is
actually written in a a framework called
tensorflow caras um kasas is a kind of a
higher level API than tensor flow and
exactly the same
application you can actually find it in
uh for pytorch uh if you go to the pytor
website uh but for now in this specific
case we're going to go with caras now
now uh the data set that we're going to
be working with is the so-called an
evolution of the very famous data set
called mnist the mnist data set was
generated and created uh for um allowing
um to to actually perform multiclass
classification on and digits uh from 0
to 9 therefore we have 10 classes and
what has happened is that over the years
uh lots of uh you know modeling uh of
lots of modeling activity the
performance the classification
performance and accuracy in that kind of
data set um saturated to the point that
cannot really be used as a data set
anymore at least for this specific
simple task we have here which is
multiclass classification so people have
thought about uh how we can create a bit
more challenging data set and they came
out U with the So-Cal fashionist which
is uh exactly the same in terms of the
uh imagery that we are feeding into uh
the X's our X's here are 28 by 28 pixels
grayscale images and instead of and
digits we have uh the um uh fashion
items and here you scroll down a little
bit you can uh first of all you can load
the data set with just a single line of
code uh and uh here are the 10 classes
that we will be concerned with uh in
this specific uh
example all right so um we have 60,000
uh training images after we split our
data set to a train and and validation
or test as it's called here and the U uh
we can actually run uh this whole
notebook in one go or run every cell
individually as we go along so if you go
to runtime uh since we Chang it to a GPU
and press the run all buttom then uh The
Notebook will be executed and we should
actually start seeing some um examples
some outputs uh from the code cells so
here we see the U you know 28x 28 uh
pixels images that we are going to be uh
processing and so what we will do now is
we will um scroll a little bit just to
see some examples and stay at this point
that we are going to be building a Model
A predictor uh this predictor is going
to be consisting of fully connected
layers and uh this is our model over
here and what we will do is we'll uh
convert this uh lines of code into a
diagram in our uh sort of uh document
camera here and so I'm going to stop and
switch to the other scene where we have
been uh will'll be
writing and generating if you like this
uh this diagram okay so let's see we are
going to turn the page a little bit
because we are have a bit more elaborate
diagram to draw so I'm going to title
this U the
uh let me call it
a
multi-layer
multi-layer let me also bring the
microphone close by so multilayer ler
uh
classification and this is the so-called
fully
connected uh sort of
architecture so uh the model if we see
the code uh is uh going to be able to
process uh this type of data however
we are not ready yet to process images
uh so what we will do is we will flatten
this 28x 28 images so remember that we
are been dealing with we have been given
this
28 by 28 pixels
images uh sort of representing some kind
of fashion item
um something like that and uh and then
we are going to um uh flatten that kind
of image to create a vector so the first
thing that happens is that we take this
uh X let me call it X Prime for a lack
of a better letter and we will pass it
through the
flatten function to create an X and if
this x Prime is 20 by 28 well if you
multiply 28 by 28 you have you're coming
up with a number called 768 okay so it
is going to be
768 * 1 that's my Vector over here and
then from that point onwards we will be
applying a stacking of fully connected
or dense layers as we call them uh
earlier so we
are going to be applying uh this uh W1 *
X
followed by the so-called bias
one followed by
aelu to generate the
H1 and then uh we are going to see
exactly what are the dimensions that I
want us to use over here um so in this
specific example in this specific code I
can see that they want us to use
um to to have a a dimensionality
reduction from
768 uh to
128 uh size over here so my H1 over here
is going to be a
128 *
1 all right so what is uh now going to
happen is that we have now the first
layer kind of
completed so the outut of this kind of
layer is going to uh go into another
dense layer uh but this dense layer is
going to um be the head of the network
so we will take H1 and we will pass it
through another transformation another
reduction well we know exactly the
number of Dimensions that we need to hit
since is our last layer in the network
is evidently going to be 10 because we
have 10 classes to classify we need to
have a 10 dimensional Vector uh at the
output of the of the network so we'll
see exactly how we will convert this
Vector into probabilities in a moment
but that's basically the in terms of
Dimensions at least we know what we will
end up so this is going to be
W2
H1 that's a another uh followed by some
kind of
bias that's a second layer bias and then
uh we are going to
have
uh a block that we'll be calling soft
Max that is going to produce for us the
Y heart and let me now explain what a
soft Max is and uh why we didn't have a
Ru first of all so if we had um a deeper
kind of network we would actually repeat
more than one time this kind of layer
evidently with a different kind of
dimensionality so we will go from 128
perhaps to let's say 64 and then from 64
uh down to 10 uh right now the author of
The Notebook suggested that you know one
layer is enough and I agree for the
specific um type of complexity uh of the
target function I think it's okay uh so
we don't have another layer uh uh but uh
in the head over here we are going to be
facing and and solving the following
kind of problem so we are going to have
some uh let me call them uh this Vector
over here Z1 as we always we're calling
Z the soal vector called that holds all
the logics
and Z2 and by
Logics uh broadly speaking we talking
about a sort of
unnormalized uh probabilities um that is
coming out of this uh dot product and
this is um this Vector Z2 here evidently
has dimensionality of 10 * 1 okay so let
me write this down 10 * 1 so what we
want to produce at the output is a
posterior probability and this posterior
probability we already have met many
times in the binary classification case
so if we had a binary classification
case well evidently we needed to just
produce a scalar at the output uh where
the Y hat will be the probability of the
positive class given
x uh however over here we are not going
to have a scaler we need to have 10
probabilities so we need to produce a
probability distribution so that's the
first important uh point so the
body uh which is uh
this let me call this the body let me
call this the
head is
generating if you like the uh uh some
dimensions in fact I would I would call
yeah let let me let me just call this
the head okay that's fine um it takes
128 uh dimensional Vector at the input
the H1 and converts it into a logic
Vector Z2 uh before fitting into this
soft Max block uh that soft Max block
the responsibility of this soft Max
block is to create uh this posterior
probability
distribution and here I have drawn the
probability distribution at the Y at the
output in other words the probability of
Y given X comma let's say Theta which is
Theta is the set of parameters of our uh
Network and uh this is going to be
something like that some probability
must function like that evidently will
be a proper probability distribution so
the summation uh let's say from J is
equal to Zer to capital K which in this
case is N9 uh of the um p with index J
over here is going to be 1.0
and the soft Max now Block in order to
introduce this kind of soft Max block we
need to kind of under at the end of the
day start from what we are trying to
achieve here so we definitely want to
report the largest possible index in uh
uh that one if you like the battle among
all the classes that we have present
here so this is let's say the index K so
if we are to report that this would
actually perform an argmax operator so
it's
argmax over all indices
JS of the uh uh the
U the
Z that it is at the um
input and this is this Z has this um
sort of a j u capital K elements and and
this is uh this is going to be the class
that we are going to report if we uh had
only the requirement to do a hard
decision so we are to do a requirement
to do a hard decision let's say the K
class is the class which is actually
present over there that's what have
reported based on this uh elements of
the Z Vector we have selected if you
like the maximum Vector but um typically
we would do not want to do that we would
not definitely report a class let's say
that this is this specific fashion item
but at the same time report some form of
a confidence how confident we are about
our prediction and that is something
that we also have done in binary
classification so the way to think about
uh the soft Max is some kind of a softer
version of
argmax uh and we are going to just write
now the um
equation that this block is implementing
this block is a vector input Vector
output block so it will be a soft Max of
Z let's say uh
J it is the ratio of e to the power of
CJ um and uh divided by the
summation over all uh JS in fact instead
of using the J over here let me use the
small letter k
as the uh as the
index so small letter K and uh this is e
to the power of
CJ so what we do um in English is to
just how to translate this equation in a
kind of intuitive way we are going to
convert all the logic into positive
numbers that's basically what the
numerator is doing and we are going to
normalize them so that at the end of the
day the
summation of uh what comes out of the
soft Max which is basically this
probability is equal to 1.0 so that's
basically what the soft Max is doing and
visually we could um interpret it as
follows if we do not care about any
confidence we are effectively reporting
the maximum possible class uh the
maximum class uh index uh the the the
index across from the maximum element
here so we are putting a some form of we
are ignoring all of the other indices
all of the other
classes and uh we put is it is as if
we're putting this kind of a window
around this class and there okay 100%
I'm 100% confident that it is this class
that is present in my uh input over here
um in the soft Max um we are going to uh
definitely consider the heights of the
other uh
logits uh the normalized logits and and
that kind of makes sense if my uh over
here I have a
0.3 and uh all the others are let's
say uh
0.2 or or even 0.1 and uh there's one
other class that is actually
0.29 then it actually Mak sense to not
be 100% confident that this is the uh
class that is actually present because
hey there is another index which is
almost as as good as as what you're
going to be reporting here so that's
what the soft Max is actually doing is
actually placing some form of a software
window around uh the U reported uh
classes the reported probabilities and
uh that is what at the end of the day uh
we are uh that's the reason why we are
going to definitely report uh
much much smaller confidence than 100%
with the soft
Max let's trite it
down
softmax is
producing a
softer
version of
arcmax we are going to of course still
report that class K won the battle but
we are going to also report a number
next to it which is definitely much less
than 100% so when we have an output
which is you know all the classes are
are very very similar but only one is
like slightly above the others uh then
we are going to report a much much lower
confidence uh about our prediction for
that specific class than compared to the
case where all the other classes are
very suppressed and this class has uh
really uh sort of of w the battle uh
inside our uh
predictor back to our code over here we
have translated this section of the code
to a block diagram we have explained all
the elements of this and uh uh
subsequently what we are actually doing
is we are compiling this model using an
Optimizer uh over here the author
selected Adam is an Adaptive um learning
rate kind of scheme very similar to
stochastic grade descent so if you
replace Adam with stochastic gr descent
you know not really many things will
change and uh the U we're actually using
the uh non binary version of the Cross
entropy um loss function we have seen uh
which uh is a bit different than the
binary cross entropy but is you know
almost identically in the same because
we are instead of having two class over
here we have
and having two terms in the binary
crossentropy loss we have 10 classes and
and therefore we have a summation of 10
terms inside this categorical cross
entropy loss function um and then of
course we are using a metric which is
the accuracy metric we are going to
train the model with the do fit API
which is uh all the way from pyit learn
inherited and this is U being used here
with a certain number of epochs
and having uh the uh evaluation done
here and printed out that's a 87%
accuracy what we have achieved here and
we are uh then able to do predictions so
we're going to see some outputs uh which
evidently there will be some y hat
output that we are producing so we have
um uh let's say using test images we are
able to use to do predictions and let's
do the predictions for the first image
uh which is index Z Z of my test data
set this is evidently going to produce
an array of 10 numbers and these numbers
are the probabilities which I just drew
uh the in the in this kind of a
probability Mass function a few moments
ago and uh that's uh basically it we are
going to definitely uh use the argmax
operator to report uh the class in this
case it is the winning class is index 9
and uh as you can see here we have a
very good situation uh we are
98.89%
confident uh that this is the U correct
class and this is uh the result of the
soft Max block as we discussed so this
is the uh I'm guessing the some uh plots
of this posterior probability there are
some small probabilities around class 5
and Class 7 uh and definitely we have
the specific class which is angle boot
over here and we are also seeing um
mistake that the predictor actually has
made for another uh uh example uh I
believe the example here is
uh um probably some other some other
test image it doesn't really matter
exactly which one uh where we have
actually reported uh that uh this is a
sneak sneer and uh in fact uh although
it is a sneaker we reporting that this
is going this is a sandal okay that's
the category five all right so we are
just doing exactly the same for many
images and we are concluding uh this uh
this this
notebook um that's basically it we we
have uh just went through our first uh
application that is actually using fully
connected layer years and we are going
now to go U into discussing a little bit
on how uh the internal internals of this
kind of training procedure uh are
working more specifically we are going
to be concerned a little bit with the uh
calculation of the gradient which is um
present in stochastic gr descent and we
will look at a operation which is called
back propagation operation that it will
uh calculate this gradient uh very
efficiently for us