in this video we will introduce
reinforcement learning and uh
reinforcement learning is definitely a
natural uh conclusion to the topic of
planning with interaction and definitely
uh follows after uh the series of videos
that we have developed on Mark of
decision processes as uh in mdp we have
been assuming full knowledge of the
problem Dynamics and reward functions
and over here we'll start removing that
kind of assumption and we will be called
to estimate those quantities from
experiences so some of this experiences
initially will take the form of
sampling uh and so we'll look at Monte
Carlo methods and uh the temporal
difference type of methods as two
instances of sampling and then we will
introduce a flexible approximation to
those estimates in the form of neural
networks and conclude the discussion
with uh deep reinforcement
learning like we have done in the mdp
also in reinforcement learning we will
divide if you like these uh
considerations into two steps one is the
so-called prediction step where our job
is really now to estimate the
corresponding value functions either the
V functions or the Q functions now
because these functions are going
to assume no knowledge of any model
Dynamics and therefore will be estimates
we need to learn them the Learned
function functions are typically uh
denoted with capital letters instead of
small letters so we will be using
capital V and capital Q for those so and
we will start with what is actually
called the uh first one um method which
is called the Monte
Carlo or
MC uh method for the prediction
problem the prediction
problem all right so and according to
this kind of method and just a recap uh
from the other video when we were
looking at the mdp we had this uh um
equation for the V uh function that a
small V uh of the uh for every state
s and this is an expectation over all
policies of uh the returns uh from that
of
State uh which is the return GT given
that we are in state
s okay and uh as a kind of remainder the
you know policies we have plenty of
policies to that are in any any problem
uh like let's say for example we have 1
2 3 four five states and let's say if we
had two actions per state either left
let's say or right uh then uh we we
could have here um
two uh to the power of 1 2 3 4 5 2 to
the power of
five uh or uh uh 32 uh
policies 32 possible policies in in
general we will have as many as the
cardinality of the set a of actions to
the cardinality of the set of States uh
so as you can understand the number of
policies that exist uh in any mdp
problem is actually quite could be quite
large and therefore one of the reason
why we are actually looking at these uh
approximations here later on is to make
sure that we have we're converting an
invisible uh to be solved problem um
into a problem that can be reasonably
expected to be practical infusible to
solve uh you know with with those
approximations so back to the sort of
mon Carlo of prediction problem this was
uh when we knew the Dynamics and
therefore what we were doing uh there is
to uh you to do actually um a
onestep the so-called uh Bellman
expectation uh kind of
backup where for every action we were
ended ended up in uh some uh State S
Prime the next state and this was U
effectively uh after the action is taken
we were migrating to S Prime and we were
recovering some kind of reward and of
course the
policy uh was um responsible for
transitioning for taking if you like
that those uh one of the available kind
of actions to us from that state
s and uh so uh the the
so-called uh estimate estimate of V Pi
of s ended up with a Bellman equation
expectation
equation um if you like that was
basically the dynamic programming the
so-call dynamic programming
solution ended up uh being a kind of a
bootstrapping uh equation and we call
that Bo strapping equation the fact that
we were using uh the V Pi of S Prime to
calculate the V Pi of
s and if I trace back uh that specific
equation uh I will we call this uh
iterative policy evaluation when we were
discussing in that video the mdp uh
policy evaluation for State value
functions of course we can we have an
equivalent one for the Q functions there
and actually you can see very clearly uh
that the VK of S Prime over here is
actually being used to calculate the
updated uh value function for the state
s and this is basically what we call by
bootstrapping in essence we are
suggesting that I don't have to in order
to calculate all these kind of averages
I need to just know the value function
of this accessors kind of states in
order for me to calculate this one and
uh I don't need to expand all the way uh
into the diagram because in the you know
effectively uh this state at some point
it was
calculated uh it it it it took the the
the s32 for example took the um the
place of s33 and it was itself evaluated
uh at at some uh previous kind of
iteration so we are uh pretending that
s32 is the kind of a sort of root State
over here but effectively what we did if
you recall was to um evaluate all states
okay so all states these V's are now
vectors and they are evaluating all
states uh at the same time okay so
that's basically what was the
bootstrapping um and uh and equivalently
we can actually see a diagram over here
just to um sort of uh that kind of
demonstrates that kind of what I just
said with a dynamic programming we have
full expansion very wide expansion of
the um of the tree where the at the root
of the tree is a state that we are
evaluating the value function of and uh
uh here we are bootstrapping that value
from the successor States as we uh just
discussed um and the intuition behind
this and obviously in the dynamic kind
of programing the whole intuition is
that you can always start from some kind
of a simple problem uh where let's say
say you are kind of close to some kind
of a terminating kind of state that you
kind of know the reward and there is
because it's terminating you are not
interested on uh any future rewards
there's no such future if you like for
you uh and then you can uh um if you
know the value functions of these kind
of States you can calculate the value
functions of the states which are above
you uh and VI are the kind of a
bootstrapping method and then you're
going into more and more larger and
larger kind of U problems for uh more
and more difficult problems than uh what
you started with but as I said uh in
reality we are not breaking down the
problem into sub problems but we are
iteratively solving uh this uh Bellman
equation uh iterative polic valuation
based on bman
equation now in Mont Carlo State value
prediction what we will do since we
don't have the Dynamics and and
effectively the Dynamics are actually
were used uh to calculate the U you know
the the sort of the bootstrapping and
the previous in the in the case of
dynamic programming the value function
what we actually going to do over here
is we are going to um uh sample uh to uh
create if you like experiences um and
the Assumption here is that we can first
of all that we have if you like a
simulator um that will be able to uh
sample experiences from the the system
so the model is being used only at a
sampling level to generate this
experiences and it is a much much easier
uh sort of proposition as compared to
estimating these models uh or learning
if you like the the the model
Dynamics and and and so and what we will
do is for every state uh and also State
and action pair that we are vising for
the corres for the V and the
corresponding Q functions what we will
do is we'll keep scores what are those
scores as as what are the uh returns
that we have experienced uh after those
States and keeping a score of of these
kind of States uh then it will allow us
to uh calculate the value function as we
we'll see another distinguishing Factor
over here is that uh in order for us to
get to the sort of sample return
uh we will need to uh reach if you like
the terminating State and therefore we
are talking about and sort of generating
kind of episodes of U uh and of some
kind of U length uh and then we will be
able to retrieve uh those um returns uh
per episode and then average across many
many thousands of episodes in order for
us to be able to approximate as much as
we can uh the value function so
effectively we are going to
be
approximating and let me make this kind
of as I reach the end the terminating
kind of
state we are going to be approximating
this expectation over here with uh the
many trajectory sums like averages
across many trajectories and let's call
this the return across each trajectory
starting let's say uh from the moment we
were in in state t sorry in state s at
time T let's say this will be the return
on trajectory let's call this trajectory
uh tow also trajectory is a term which
is used extensively in motion control
but uh a synonym of that is the
episode which is a bit more common
across reinforcement learning so on that
kind of episode Dow we will have some
kind of a summation
of the U
discounted so K is equal let's say to Z
to uh T minus capital T minus one let's
assume that this is the length that this
trajectory kind of lasted of all
discounted kind of
future
rewards okay so this is um going to be
um the uh return and then uh what we'll
do now is we'll write
uh the update kind of uh method the
update kind of formulation for each of
the elements of the state value function
so the step first step is that you know
for
each time
step uh for each time step
t uh
that s is phys
it in an
episode we increment we keep this uh
score via this kind of
counter
increment the
counter n
ofs the effective counts the visitations
the number of visitations that kind of
state and
calculate the total
return as uh g capital t of s is equal
GT
ofs plus GT
and effectively uh we are the second
step is that at the
end of
thousands thousands is an example many I
will call it
episodes the value we calculate the
estimate which is now capital V as we
said capital V of
s it is G T of s divided by n of
s and as the number of times that we are
U sort of um n ofs is visited is
becoming larger and larger then we will
effectively converge
this as an in other words of s tends to
Infinity this will
converts to V pi
of
s okay and I think I forgotten to add
the pi over here in the capital V and we
also do uh the following trick to called
incremental uh mean sample mean or mean
approximation
where I think we this EXA it's exactly
the same trick that we had done in
another video uh when we were dealing
with recursive State estimation and kind
of a calman filters where we are uh
effectively writing a statistic in a
kind of recursive form the same thing
can be done in either the mean or the
covariance or correlation matrices here
is the just to remind everyone we can
actually write the uh sample mean
of the
KF uh sample that is actually coming in
uh from 1 to K as 1 /
K of
summation from let's say J is equal 1 to
K oops
XJ let's say the XJ was a sample all
right and then we have uh can write this
as one 1/ small letter K of breaking
down the sum into um J is = 1 to K minus
1 XJ plus
XK and then if we do the another step we
will be able to write this as the
previous
mean the previous mean
estimate + 1 / small letter k
of x
k
minus new K minus
one so the previous uh estimate plus 1 /
K the current sample minus the previous
estimate and back then in that kind of
other video we actually call this some
kind of indication of the calman gain if
you recall all this kind of stuff so
it's exactly the same formula and if you
use this actually formula over here
we'll be able to uh do the uh um sort of
uh the up the value
function with the Monte Carlo method can
be written
as uh n of s these two steps is equal to
n of s + one incrementing if you like
the counter every time we visit State
s okay and the second is to
calculate the V of
s let's say V Pi of
s is equal
to uh V Pi of uh V
Pi of S
Plus let me call this
Alpha GT which is the current return as
it is estimated for that specific for
that specific uh episode
minus V Pi of
s so the
um so this is the previous
estimate uh these are the previous
estimates now obviously we can
distinguish there with the um an index K
but in implementation you have a left
hand side uh and the right hand side to
be um sort of separating in a in a let's
say implementation in in software so you
don't need necessarily to put the
indices so Alpha in this case is one
over n
ofs and this uh we can call it the
forgetting
factor and obviously um this forgetting
factor is less than one this allows us
to have a bit more flexibility on uh how
many terms we're able to
average uh and uh we can actually call
the so this
implementation uh the
running
sample
mean of the state value
function also worth noting a couple of
things from this kind of formula the
first is that uh the estimate no there's
no bootstrapping
in other words we do
not
use an
estimate
of the value
function of a another
state so there's no bootstrapping here
and uh as effectively the estimates
between states are kind of independent
of each other and this is also kind of
an advantage because computationally
wise we can actually in any problem that
we have to estimate value functions for
a subset of the states or even just a
single kind of state we're able to do so
with M Carlo methods and the second is
that the value
function can
only be updated
at the
end of
each
episode because this is um empasis on
only because this basically where we get
that kind of return and this is
basically something that we we will work
to kind of provide an enhancement on
that uh with a temporal difference
methods now as an example of of what is
actually called a also um a simple
example where we don't have any explicit
kind of actions over here or
decisions uh where uh this is actually
called Mark of reward
process uh we have um a kind of
a straight line kind of sequence of
states where the agent may start
from a state
over here sh here A
B
C
D E and there is
a actually this is a one way
arrow goes into a terminating State on
the right hand side where uh the
transition the reward over here is one
and it's a terminating State all of the
other rewards are actually zero
and actually the agent starts with C
starts with that's a starting state of
the agent and there is
a a left terminating State as well that
is
also uh Express reward of zero but over
here in that right terminating State we
have a reward of one and uh we would
like to come up with u an you know the
the state value function estimate using
let's say first kind of a dynamic
programming and uh what we will do is we
will use uh the formula let's say V Pi
of
s is summation over let's say
actions of the policy of a given
s over here we have uh two uh potential
uh actions that the agent can take
either we go left or right at every
state so these
are the general formula but it has to be
kind of specialize to the there's a
transition
model as we said and then we have here
r+
gamma V Pi of S
Prime this was the kind of a bootstrap
this is a dynamic programming solution
and Gamma here is also equal to
one all right so
the effectively
um so AG also need to write also that
agent and go left or
right uh one step uh one state that it
step with equal
probability okay all right so that's
basically uh the policy um so this is
uh let me call it Pi of a given
s is uh 0.5 for
left and uh 0.5 5 for
right all right so and I can actually uh
take now each of these
um possible States and actually write
down what will actually be uh that um
formula will actually tell us so this
will
be and this is this is also the before I
do so I can actually also write the kind
of a backup diagram for every state s
I have uh two actions either left or
right and for each action I may end up
in
uh potentially in two neighboring
states sometimes only one because it's
terminating but uh that's basically uh
in general the backup diagram this is
the S
Prime uh this is the transition model
here P of S
Prime comma R given s comma
a and uh this is the policy Pi okay so
this is uh so according to this formula
V Pi of
a s will be a is going to
be uh for a I can actually go
um right uh or left so if I go um Left I
will have here I can go left with
probability uh
one2 and over here I can actually have
um the immediate reward go left will
actually be
zero uh will be zero plus gamma which is
one uh
VP of T let's call it l let's let's call
this uh TL and this call this TR for
right okay so
plus and the other one is
uh2 of 0 +
VP of B that's the other action and uh
this will actually be
um since the VP of TL is zero and this
will be V
Pi of B /
2 that's kind of equation
one uh the V Pi of
B will be I'm going to write now
quicker V Pi of a + 12 0 + V Pi of
C which is V Pi of a plus v Pi of
c/ 2
that's equation
two and then we have V Pi of C is equal
V Pi of B plus v Pi of D now I think
everything is clear over two equation
3 V Pi of D is equal V Pi of C plus v Pi
of
e over two 4 and finally B pi
e is equal V Pi of D + 1 which is coming
from the fact that we are going to into
TR ided by two and that's equation
five and um it's easy to solve this
problem uh from one I can have that V Pi
of B is equal to 2 V Pi of
a from two I have that 4 V V Pi of a is
equal V Pi of a plus v Pi of
C in other words V Pi of C is equal 3 V
Pi of
a from three I have V Pi of uh D is
equal 4 V Pi of
a and from four I have V Pi of V is
a and from five I have V Pi of a is = to
1 /
6 and therefore I'm able to solve all of
these other uh
Expressions uh this is going to be 4 6
or
2/3 V Pi of
a
2/3 every Pi of
a and this will be
a 12
I'm sorry this is just 2/3 not V by of
f just
2/3 this is
uh is
1/2 and this is uh
1/3 okay so that's basically six
1/3 um
1/2
2/3 and that's 2/3 also okay and that's
basically the solution of the value
function as a vector of across all
states I make a mistake over here it
this
2/3 +
1 uh
half which is 56
okay so that's the vector of
solutions and what we will see with
Monte Carlo I'm just going to show you
the graph of which is basically the left
side kind of graph here uh what we will
see with mon Carlo is that we are going
to uh this is basically what we
estimated the black line over
here uh for all the states this is
basically the True
Values uh from the dynamic programming
solution and what the the M car actually
will start is will start with some kind
of initial kind of vector of
values and um it will start um you know
trying to estimate the value function
based on a number of trajectories with
this
averaging uh the running average that we
have just discussed so this is with one
trajectory or one episode 10 episodes
the green line and the 100 episode uh
estimates are the ones which are
obviously uh going to be coming closer
and closer into the the true uh value
function