in this video we now go into the second
um sort of method of prediction we will
address first of all the prediction
problem and then the control problem uh
that kind of naturally flows after Monte
Carlo that is called temporal difference
and this is kind of an important
category of of of methods that that I
think they are going to at some point
merge together uh with other approaches
we have seen in in in solving if you
like a more elegantly the prediction uh
the value function prediction problem we
have seen in the mon car prediction that
the mod carand of a value function
update is um as
follows uh let's say V
uh
Pi first
T is uh equal
V Pi of
S Plus
Alpha the return after this uh
State
minus the previous
estimate St okay so this is um what was
happening in the Monte Carlo approach
and what we actually uh is happening in
the temporal difference is that again of
of course this means that we have to
wait until the actual realization of the
episode kind of happens and all and all
the experience kind of formulated within
the episode until we are able to update
this kind of value function in the
temporal difference uh what we actually
do is we have another um sort of an
advant what what it turns out to be an
advantage is that we don't have to wait
until uh the the the episode completes
and the equation becomes V I of
St is equal to V Pi capital V that is of
St
minus I'm sorry plus
Alpha of uh the
following uh the this
is RT +
1 plus gamma V of St + 1
minus V of
s
now you know so what is really the big
deal about it uh the you can consider
the temporal difference learning um
approach as kind of some kind of a
hybrid between what we have we're doing
in Mont Carlo and what we are doing in U
a dynamic programming and in the dynamic
programming kind of video we have seen
that uh there is boot strapping and here
you see the bootstrapping in front of
you so we are using the value function
of the next state and it's estimate if
you like in order to put strap uh the
value function of uh the state that we
are interested in and uh and at the same
time um we are effectively uh
maintaining the sort of the Monte Carlo
kind of approach in the sense that we
are still
um generating if you like experiences uh
that we would like to um sort of uh
consider in that evaluation let me WR
write this down the so-called One
Step more specifically we'll refer to
this as
td0 temporal difference methods
combines the bootstrapping
of dynamic
programming and the
sampling of Monte
Carlo to give you a kind of a an example
from real life that you can always kind
of refer to um and kind of map it to
that kind of equation so let's assume
that I'm coming from um
Brooklyn so let's call
this uh the
um SB the state that I am um in Brooklyn
right now and uh at some point I need to
uh go back to uh New Jersey in uh and
and therefore I have two options either
to take an
action uh to go through the Brooklyn
Bridge or to take another action and go
through the Manhattan Bridge so that's
my
A1 and
A2 and A2 is
Manhattan and let's also now Define two
other states the past Brooklyn and the
past man cut and Bridge states that I
end up after I kind of crossed uh those
two Bridges so just like what happens in
in kind of real life the moment you go
through um a kind of a significant kind
of milestone in your commute let's say
crossing a very uh too busy kind of
landmarks over here uh then you can
actually update your estimate okay now
that I have passed the Brooklyn Bridge
now I have another uh you know 40
minutes to reach my kind of destination
then uh that is this value over here uh
the fact that you uh can now update the
SB using another guess so we are
effectively estimating using yet another
estimate and this is basically what the
bootstrapping is so the um we kind of
receive our reward here uh which is this
the moment we uh sort of pass we
actually taking this action and we are
uh sort of of uh Landing into these S
Prime
States and uh we are actually using the
estimates of these uh States in order
for for us to uh bootstrap and update in
uh the estimate of the state again we're
doing uh one step unrolling uh here and
this is uh the what a diff temporal
difference actually is um so that's um
uh so now I think we should come to the
discussion as to
um is that temporal difference method um
has any other Advantage compared to
Monto Carlo obviously we don't have to
wait until the episode ends until uh for
us to update sometimes the episodes are
so long uh that uh you know the that's
kind of a significant Advantage
effectively making the temporal
difference method I will call it as part
of what's called online
learning uh the other uh kind of
significant difference is that um it
turns out that uh they do converge um
into the uh so there's not really uh any
issue of using a guess or an estimate to
bootstrap and update another estimate
they it has been shown although we're
not going to do the uh you know any
detailed discussion here the temporal
difference methods are uh converging and
uh in in fact depending on the setting
uh of uh this Alpha over there if it is
kind of a small value it converges and
and everything is fine the one thing
that um you can actually see the
convergence is by running an example uh
in the previous video we have seen uh an
a mark of reward process and uh using if
you like two terminal States and I think
it's worthwhile going through uh that
example with with a temporal difference
now and we've seen how the Carlo kind of
approximates the sort of True Value
function and I just want to show
you uh the uh sort of how the Monte
Carlo and temporal difference methods
now
compare and so this is where the Monte
Carlo is depends on the values values of
alpha because we are effectively um
waiting until the episode uh kind of
finishes uh then we have um a
significant kind of I will call it
convergence slower convergence okay so
um as compared to temporal difference
where actually we have uh you know
definitely faster convergence and you
can actually see some Behavior which
kind of
matches uh the stochastic approximation
uh type of type of algorith like the
ones that are uh those
uh where the lower the alpha is then we
have slower kind of convergence but then
the residual kind of error that we
actually get in terms of U root Min
square error that is between the true
function and the estimated value
function is lower than perhaps
converging faster um and that's kind of
a classic Behavior with a good radios
but bottom line is a temporal difference
seems to be performing uh better than
Monte Carlo methods before proceeding
into closing this soall prediction
problem with temporal difference
learning methods I think it's worthwhile
addressing an enhancement which kind of
brides the gap between what we've seen
in Monte Carlo and the singl step
temporal difference learning that we
just saw and this actually called TD of
Lambda it's uh kind of known for for
with this notation uh and we'll see
exactly what Lambda is in a moment but
the main advantage of this enhancement
is that it
decouples uh the uh sort of action um
actions from uh value updates so the you
know in the single step process we are
taking an action at every uh time step
and also we are updating the value uh at
every time step and this does not really
make a necessarily the best it is not
necessarily the best choice we actually
you may well prefer to keep uh the
actions coming in as frequently as
possible but at the same time to uh only
update States when there are significant
updates that taking place and not every
time
step one small correction I wanted to
post on the formula of the return the
right formula is actually this one and
uh this correction was needed because
when we went to episodic experiences
later on in reinforcement learning
uh we uh kind of discovered that this
was an incorrect formula so there was a
couple of typos here uh so that's the
right one so I'm going to post that uh
on the MTP uh section uh and we have not
really used explicitly this form of that
formula anyway in a subsequent kind of
discussion so I think we should be okay
and this is another uh place where we
have actually had a couple of typos on
the return uh now when we have an
episode capital T of duration capital T
and uh we are effectively calculating
the return starting from uh when we are
at State at time step t Okay so that's
uh that's the second uh type over there
that we uh need to be aware of and this
one will actually uh carry over uh when
we're discussing uh now the uh returns
uh for uh multiple steps multiple step
time diff uh different temporal
difference uh methods
so after end
steps our return actually will be uh
written as GT let me write it as uh
after end steps it will be RT + 1+ GMA
RT + 2 plus dot dot dot plus gamma to
the power of n minus1 r of t +
n plus gamma n
v s of t plus n so I actually wrote also
uh and then I kind of recorded uh some
other um equation this equation is
effectively the one that kind of
summarizes how we will actually be using
the endstep return uh in the updated
equation for um the the N step uh
temporal difference method and as you
can see the only thing that actually
changes over here is that uh instead of
having this uh term which is actually we
call TD Target uh we have the end uh
return the endep return in its place so
the endstep return in its place for n is
equal to 1 effectively it is the RT + 1
+ gamma V St + 1 so we are back into the
TD uh zero as we'll call it we
understand exactly why the zero the
Lambda is equal Z corresponds to this
case U and uh and that's basically the
uh sort of the the the end result of the
endep return so now we can actually uh
decouple uh the um estimate of the value
function and the bootstrapping actually
we do over there uh for and and the um
and and and the sort of action that we
are taking so we can continue take the
actions at every step and uh uh while we
will be updating after end steps uh the
value function okay so that's basically
that equation allows us to do so now out
of some uh studies which are not going
to be presented here uh but they are
definitely included in the uh Saturn's
book for those who are interested to
Deep dive a bit uh further they have
shown that the way that the um end step
what is really the best end to choose
okay so it's basically uh is it the
hyper parameter how we are actually go
about defining this hyperparameter and
what actually has been found is that uh
there are certain kind of trade-offs uh
uh between choosing the sort of n is
equal to one the one step and having
large n and as you can understand and
the algorith that we are effectively
concluded um out of this discussion is
just called the TD Lambda algorith which
is basically what it does is that
instead of selecting one out of the N it
tries to average
many uh returns endep returns many ends
in other words so the let's call it the
many end kind of algorith or Lambda
algorithm and the way that it is um uh
being
presented is that uh we are actually
defining the average return with a a
weight that it is uh negative
exponential as it actually shown and of
course applies up to uh it is such that
the summation of all the weights in is
averaging sometimes to one and uh the
equation of the waiting of the returns
to average them is this equation over
here which is the way it is actually
plotted over here uh on the as a as a
time as a Time index a Time step index
up to the of course the um uh episode
kind of length and now let's write down
the final uh kind of TD Lambda uh update
equation and also show that with Lambda
is equal to Z this corresponds to the
one step temporal difference also known
as TD of Zer and with Lambda is equal to
one is roughly equivalent to the Monte
Carlo so the equation is
V let say t+
n since we were also adding policy Pi
let's add it s is equal to
v t + nus1
of S Plus
Alpha
g
t of
Lambda
minus uh uh
V uh of t + N - one
Pi of
s okay so that this is the equation and
now um we said that we're going to uh
Define also the GT of
Lambda which we have seen already we
have seen already the equation now we
need to show that for Lambda is equal to
Z this corresponds
to notation Y is DD of zero the zero
here corresponds to Lambda or to the on
step uh
TD and uh so we'll take the the equation
that we have already quoted so this is
uh GT of
Lambda was- 1 - Lambda summation from n
is = to
1 uh to
Infinity this is n is equal to 1 in
other words Lambda n -1 GT of
N and we'll write it as as this equation
here which is exactly identical to this
but we just changed the notation to be a
bit more compatible to the Saturn kind
of book notation where um he is actually
using this kind of uh uh notation to
indicate a return from the returns from
T to t plus n okay so um this between
the T and T plus n kind of a time step
that is okay so effectively the the
returns in TD in EP TD are trated trated
into two portions one is really the true
uh returns with all the discounted kind
of rewards and the other is this
remaining term or the missing term which
is approximated by the discounted kind
of value function and as you can see
from the core side the notation kind of
makes sense because the GT from T to t +
one is effectively what we had for the
one step the t+ two for the two step the
three step t plus three for the uh
three-step TD and so on all the way to
uh the U TD Infinity in fact and we'll
see exactly how we will account for that
remaining what for the for the for the
terms after uh the uh terminating kind
of state we can actually now break this
uh summation over this Infinity terms
into two parts and actually this is
actually shown over here when we have
actually have plotted this weights that
we are line uh into two parts the first
part is what is actually shown here as
the white portion and the second part is
what everything is after that the kind
of a shaded region over here and of
course the key term over there is the
capital T which is the episode length
and so what we need to do now is we go
back to the Whiteboard and start you
know writing a couple of considerations
down so for all
indices from n is equal
1 for n is equal to 1
2 uh
t uh minus t minus
one uh the
returns
are are weighted
with this kind of decaying Lambda
factors we I say decaying because as you
can see it was a decaying kind of
geometric progression of that uh because
Lambda is less than or equal to one they
get weighted with uh the they're
weighted
by the factors uh the the the following
so I'm going to take this I'm going to
take this and break it down into two
parts the first part is
1 1us
Lambda
summation uh from u n is equal to
to uh n to capital
T minus t
-1 Lambda to n + n minus one and
uh times G of T of t +
n that's the first term and then we'll
see uh that the second term is uh 1
minus
Lambda Lambda to t -
tus1 GT
okay so this is basically the the
expression and let me just uh
effectively highlight the following as
we can see uh anything that it is um you
know why we actually came to this kind
of uh you know consideration especially
with respect to the last term over there
uh so the first thing is
that uh
anything any instant T where uh we are
going Beyond if you like the terminating
kind of state so any anything that
anything that it is with IND this is t +
n greater than or equal to
T or effectively
n greater than equal to T minus t then
all the
returns all
returns are in fact
um the full
return
CT course all the rewards after the
terminating state are actually zero and
of course this means that the full
return uh is uh is basically what is uh
what it corresponds to to to those cases
so that is the reason why I actually
wrote from n is equal to 1 to capital T
minus t minus1 because this is just
before this condition gets to be
satisfied right so it's everything uh
before this uh State over here as we
actually can see on the site the first
Factor the first uh term if you like in
this summation we just broke up
corresponds to the weights that we have
applied they're actually shown here in
this white
region of this like you know
geometrically decaying uh if you like
weight curve and then the last term the
last term corresponds to uh this weight
over here that anything
is beyond uh capital T which is the
episode will actually be weighted by uh
1 minus Lambda Lambda to T capital T
minus t minus one and that's basically
what we also have um uh kind of
mentioned here on the site in terms of
equation all right so this is basically
um uh everything that we actually can
mention regarding uh TD of n this is the
um sort of endep TD and what actually we
need to do next is we need to start uh
considering the control problem and uh
this will be done in a in a different
video