ear video we have seen statistical
learning at least in the supervised
learning uh approach and we have seen uh
linear models for aggression and
generalized linear models for
classification in this video we are
going to expand now to a a type of
predictors which are differentiable end
to end so we are not going to be
requiring just the loss function to be
differentiable with respect to the
parameters but we also going to be
requiring all of the components of this
prediction architecture to be
differentiable with respect to
parameters these predictors are part of
what we call the connectionism
philosophy uh where we are actually
putting together individual units that
we'll call sigmoidal neurons that when
they are connected together in a proper
way that we see exactly what proper
means they are exhibiting some I will
call it Universal approximation uh
properties so let's get started with
producing just a single Sig sigmoidal
kind of neuron and uh let's for that
let's go to the
site so the actual neuron that we see
here on the side on the top figure over
here is a fairly complicated kind of
organism it has inputs that we call Dent
rites and outputs and in between inputs
and output is actually this compressive
stage that is called myelinated action
and signals are actually going from
those dentes through this action uh into
outputs and this neuron this unit is uh
going to be connected to other units
that we'll see in a moment now rosenblat
working in a government sponsor
laboratory 60 years ago uh he actually
came up with an uh architecture that
kind of resembles uh this uh organism
and we actually we have seen this type
of architecture uh before uh so let me
just uh write the kind of a d diagram on
on our sort of board right
now this first kind of stage of this
neuron
is a DOT product is sigmoidal Neuron
that is there are various kind of
neurons uh but here we're just reading
the sigmoidal version so we have the dot
product of w transpose X these are both
uh
vectors uh and explicitly we are sort of
denoting here this kind of a bias term
uh that uh is kind of explicitly shown
as B and uh the uh last stage is a
nonlinearity which is the sigmoidal
nonlinearity we have also seen in the
treatment of logistic
regression uh so typically this signal
over here is uh it's called activation
and this is also known as activation
function and
evidently just like in other we have
done up to now we have a y hat at the
output that is the predicted Target
variable and
also we know now that corresponds to the
probability of Y is equal to 1 given
X so that is uh basically the block
diagram of the sigmoidal kind of neuron
and I hope it's everyone is kind of
familiar with the dot products and all
these kind of uh discussion we had even
from kind of earlier kind of treatment
so I'm not going to expand here uh what
I think we is worthwhile actually doing
however is to try to understand how
potentially a neuron uh with everything
we have seen uh can be trained and for
that I'm going to go into web page
actually called tensorflow playground
and in that tensorflow playground I'm
going to we're going to see now how we
can actually um take this kind of neuron
this block diagram and hit it with some
kind of a data set and see what it is
able to do and how it will uh probably
not able to do certain things for us and
have some discussion about how we can
actually create a network of these
neurons so when we actually go to the
site tensor flow play ground site will
actually the first time you go into
there you'll actually see a picture such
as this and we would like to modify this
picture to just basically bring a single
neuron into that so we will have here
just uh press the minus button to
eliminate uh the uh what is called a
layer which terat we'll see shortly and
just leave a single neuron uh on that uh
sort of architecture have a single
neural architecture uh we are going to
have a sigmoidal activation
function and uh we are going to be
discussing uh the operation of this kind
of neuron in this uh small data set that
we see here it's a classification data
set with just two classes and uh just
because we would like to make things a
bit more challenging if you can increase
the noise to something like 25 you
actually get a nonlinear non linear
separated data data set and uh that is
uh
basically it uh we're going to have a
potentially a bat size of
10 okay let's leave it 10 or even we can
make it one and we are going
to avoid um introducing complication of
regularization here learning rate as we
have seen earlier should be some small
number let's say
0.01 and we just by pressing the play
button what you actually see you'll
actually see see uh the output over here
uh this is the loss function the two two
loss functions uh the training loss and
the test loss uh that are very very
quickly uh converging and this is U the
decision boundary that uh the single
neuron kind of produced uh very
straightforward uh very easy to come up
with u if you like that decision
boundary as you can see and of course
everything that we have discussed before
the stochastic grade descent is in
operation here uh so if we go back to
that um drawing board you will uh
definitely expect to see here a loss
function which is nothing else as the
binary cross entropy and uh that Banner
crossentropy being
fed uh into the stochastic grated
descent that it will uh adjust the
weights W from one iteration to the next
and uh that is all straightforward we
have done that uh before as well and uh
now let's go back to that uh
site and let's see what is uh going to
happen if we uh change a little bit the
data set we are facing and uh we have um
another two dimensional data set I
forgot earlier to mention that here we
have effectively two features two
dimensions in my X we have X1 and X2 uh
again in this new data set we have which
is uh slightly more
complicated uh let's first of all remove
the noise just to see you know uh the
data set a bit more clearly so we have
the blue class kind of centered in the
middle and it is surrounded by the
orange
glass uh and as we expect to see the um
you know the decision boundary is
definitely heavily nonlinear it's
actually in fact circular and let's try
to um do exactly the same thing um press
the play button and see exactly what is
happening um so we observe now a kind of
different Behavior we are going to start
seeing some form of loss reduction so
the neuron is actually trying its best
to uh minimize uh training and test
losses and uh here we kind of see some
kind of a decision
boundary uh but uh I I hope we all
recognize that that's not really the one
that we are uh probably going to uh
result into a very good prediction
performance and uh very good
generalization so um what is to blame
here uh and we have seen this kind of
behavior before even in the linear uh
models we have studied and uh this is uh
effectively what we see here is some
form of an underfeeding effect in other
words uh the single neuron in terms of
the number of parameters we have just
have U uh uh three parameters here two
associated with the number of dimensions
of X plus the bias term uh is really not
able to capture the complexity which is
required by the Target function and that
underlying Target function that governs
this kind of classification problem
requires probably a larger number of
parameters so that's a kind of a good
pretext to start introducing neural
networks now we are going to start
interconnecting many neurons together in
some architecture it will make uh sense
to all of
us all right so let's see we will now uh
use the single neuron that we have
seen as a unit so I'm drawing if you
like a single box over here I'm putting
the number one and inside that single
boxes everything that you see here
above all of this blocks are inside this
kind of single block uh we are going to
feed to
it the x that we've seen in this tensor
playround example and uh we are going
to feed X also to get another
neuron uh let me just draw it a a bit
kind of
differently to have a bit more space
and this is the second neuron the first
neuron
is has parameters that are inside it are
W1 and the associated kind of bias now
to make the little bit the math a bit
easier I'm not going to be dealing with
a bias term explicitly at least in this
discussion so I'm just going to show you
only
the weight w the parameter W
Vector which is uh two the
dimensionality of that is two just like
the dimensionality of X is two so the
first neuron will produce an output of I
will call it
y1 and uh the second neuron will produce
an output which will call Y2 hat these
are the two
predictions however now these outputs
will will be
combined with the help of a third
neuron neuron number
three to produce the final output which
we'll
call Y3 hatut and this neuron has its
own kind of
parameters uh
W3 okay so that's uh basically the
architecture we are going to uh to to
study a little bit and uh okay so that I
think architecture this actually make
sense we are going to definitely have a
scalar at the end this is a scalar this
is a scaler two scalers in the form of a
vector so at the input over
here we see a vector this Vector will
call it let's say let's call this Vector
H uh this Vector H is consist of y1
hat and Y2 hat this vector will we dot
product we form the dot product of H uh
with the W3 over here and follow with
the sigmoidal unit so the output of this
uh architecture is going to be this
three neural architecture is going to be
a scalar which of course is exactly what
we need uh for binary classification and
scalar between 0 and one all right so uh
in terms of uh terminology will be
calling this stacking of neurons
let me draw it like this we'll be
calling this a
layer so we effectively here we have two
layers and uh more specifically this
layer um which is uh just before the
final stage uh we are going to also be
calling it body sometimes because it
this body will consist of more than than
uh one layers typically here we just
have only one and this part over here
will be calling it a
head and more specifically this head is
a sigmoidal neuron which is doing
classification or we call it
classification here uh at this moment
okay so if we are to write down the
equation the equation of the
Y3 this is
Sigma of
W3
transpose
H that's the equation of uh the uh
neuron number three uh that is exactly
the functional form of what the neuron 3
is actually doing so here we have Sigma
and open parenthesis we
have
W13
w23 the second component of W3 transpose
transpose uh times the H1 and H2 the two
components of the H Vector which is
nothing else and then let me write it
the way I wrote it over here y1 hat and
Y2 and this is
now
Sigma of
W13 y1 hat Plus
w23
Y2 and this is nothing else now as
Sigma
W13 Well the y1 hat itself is another
sigmoid function acting on the dot
product of the first
neuron okay that's basically my
X and
this parenthesis should not be there
plus
w23 sigmoid of
W2 transpose
X that is actually uh the expression of
of the output of this kind of network of
this three neuron Network and there are
some kind of interesting observ ation
just from this kind of simple
architecture that I would like to point
out the first uh is that we definitely
see some form of nesting uh going on so
we have some kind of a nested function
we have sigmoid of
sigmoids have sigmoids of some linear
combination of other
sigmoids uh which are evidently
nonlinear functions and uh if you recall
from all our uh earlier kind of work on
generalized linear models we always had
this kind of form of w transpose f of x
now these five of x's at that time came
from the sort of wellestablished basis
function such as polinomial and so on
over here what we see is that these
effectively are the
features taking the place of these five
functions we have seen earlier so we
have two features over here combined
linearly so feature U one and feature
two and perhaps more
importantly this
um uh head this is
accepting uh and combining features and
these features have been generated from
within the network itself
so uh the network is effectively
constructing the right features such
that the classification head at the very
end uh is able to actually do this job
properly so that's actually a kind of a
fairly important observation of of uh
what we SE seen earlier and comparison
what we have seen earlier and what we
actually have right now uh the second
point so the the first one is uh nesting
the second one
is uh sort of uh I will call it
automatic
feature
generation and the third one which I
wanted to mention is that now we
have uh going to have the exactly the
same environment which we have seen
earlier in uh our where
parameters um parameter optimization so
we have evidently a binary cross entropy
uh and a stochastic grad descent but now
everything is jointly optimized so I am
going to be writing here the Theta
Vector which is consist of three other
vectors W1 W2 and
W3 of these three neurons and the
optimizer is going to be jointly
optimizing the parameters just like we
have seen earlier from just a single
neuron and uh therefore it will be
implementing uh the well known to us
equation uh of stochastic radi that we
have seen
earlier so I'm mentioning that because
very quickly uh the number of parameters
that we have here will
explode so here we have uh how many we
have just basically six parameters here
plus the three bias terms which I didn't
write explicitly let's say nine so this
stochastic radius n will actually be
searching in this nine dimensional kind
of space to find this optimal uh Theta
star gradually as we have discussed
before so the uh important
thing is the uh I think number two uh
the automatic feature generation or the
fact that the network the network itself
builds the right
representations uh
for for the head or whatever the head is
doing the head in this case is doing
classification but we'll see other
examples where the head is actually
doing regression
for the right task the task is the
responsibility of the head to implement
it um and and definitely we see here a
good small example but it actually
taught us a couple of things we have not
seen before to close the discussion
we'll go back to that uh site tensorflow
playground and recreate the architecture
we had put together so we were going to
have two layers
uh and in the first layer is going cons
consist of two neurons both neurons
accept exactly the same X as it's
actually shown over here and the output
of this uh each neuron is being combined
by the head that's the last neuron at
the top of the layer if you like okay
and uh now we are going
to uh sort of play again with this uh
experiment in this kind of more
complicated ated uh experiment uh data
set that we have uh seen earlier that a
single neuron was not really able to do
much and we are going to just press the
play button and see what
happens so again the stochastic grade
descent is now looking at this kind of a
nine-dimensional
space and um it's continues to look we
are evidently going through many many
epochs our uh training loss and test
loss um seem to have been stuck uh at
around uh
0.5 so not really uh a very good um sort
of uh Behavior
yet but we should also be patient
because you know we never I mean this
thing is actually running in the
browser um it is using yeah you know the
kind of V8 engine which is behind the
these browser to do the calculations in
kind of a JavaScript so it's not really
really the fastest
implementation and uh since we are
looking in this n-dimensional space now
I think we should give it some time yes
surely enough some local Minima seems to
have been
found at this moment so the loss kind of
dropped we start seeing some elements of
a loss function uh being significantly
now dropped and look what happens now
with a decision
boundary um the decision boundary
uh Without Really us doing that much and
then really adding these neurons became
kind of
quadratic and it's kind of almost there
in a sense that it is uh all we need to
understand is whether if I if we can
give it some more time perhaps another
local Minima which is even better than
the one that we have just experienced
will be found and uh we are going to
just let it run and um uh however we we
we can actually show some kind of a
useful trajectory now in front of us we
have seen as we are adding more
neurons uh then uh effectively we are
enhancing the modeling capabilities of
our hypothesis set so we should have now
some analogy in our mind what we have
seen in the earlier as a hypothesis set
and the um the the set of functions G
that we have discussed um are is
actually translate into an architecture
so the more complicated the architecture
uh becomes perhaps the more uh we
increase uh the number of hidden layers
or even the number of neurons which are
uh in each layer then we would expect to
see uh an ability to sort of fit more
challenging Target functions so let's
play this with uh for for a while let's
leave it leave it running over there and
then
if it founds a good um local Minima and
we can actually stop the iterations and
present it to you all right now from uh
actually let it run and then from uh
that kind of perspective I think the
next discussion would actually be to try
to create a mathematical abstraction of
these um networks that we'll be calling
fully connected Network so we need to
understand why we call them fully
connected