so in an earlier video we have seen
object detection object detection was
presented as a capability of a neural
network to present to us a stream of
Json a Json stream of where that
contains bounding box let's say
information about objects of interest
and uh in that kind of discussion we
also saw a video where uh bounding boxes
were simply appearing in this specific
frame and maybe disappearing uh in the
next frame and reappearing in the frame
after that in many Mission critical
applications it's almost impossible to
uh deal with such a kind of a
flickering um um sort of appearance of
the object detection uh output and uh
and in fact this appearance this
flickering that we observed in in the um
in those videos uh originates from the
fact that neural networks are uh sort of
reflexive uh in nature so they are
probabilistic devices and as such they
are sort of reflexive in nature so what
we will do in this kind of video is we
will investigate approaches where we are
going to uh simply uh try to correct uh
these video outputs and we will be
calling this uh discussion probabilistic
reasoning over time where the time kind
of AIS needs to be involved now to
correct for those and come up with a
video stream that contains object
detections which are uh very much
continuous and without this kind to have
flickering effects we should also
mention that the topic is a bit more
significant just correcting for missing
frames and an object detection kind of
stream I think it can expand into
covering the So-Cal covering in the gaps
the ability of humans to uh cover the
gaps with reason when they don't have
perception information let's say if I'm
uh behind an occlusion and um and I was
visible a few moments ago then every
person who is kind of watching this
scene is able to reason that you know
this other person is behind now in
inclusion um and so the kind of
discussion over here will kind of expand
into uh this type of General topic of
tracking objects in a scene so I think
it's also a good idea to uh see the uh
on our side we have this kind of block
diagram that positions the topic at
least uh the part of the topic we're
discussing in general probabilistic
reasoning over time
this is the Yellow Block over here which
follows the perception it receives the
Json stream and delivers another stream
that it is uh kind of richer uh in a
sense to the planner uh richer and
obviously more correct uh as it has
stitched together uh the um imperfect
detections that we have uh we it is
presented that we are presenting to it
uh so out of the many uh areas um that
uh we can actually categorize as
probabilistic reasoners over time and
and capabilities over here you see in
these kind of boxes will be
focusing on uh use cases that are
associated with uh tracking objects uh
as we discussed as well also the topic
of
localization uh and um needless to say
that this block is present uh in the
what we will be calling later on basian
filters as in every single robot which
is out there um and in fact it is not
only robots but it's also embedded in
your cell phones uh as uh they have they
also need to track uh various signals
which are actually being received from
the cellular and satellite
infrastructure let's now try to
establish some kind of uh terminology
and notation on the things that we need
to study uh to understand a little bit
how we going to go about addressing this
kind of a uh issue of correcting for
imperfect let's say detections or in
general tracking uh all sorts of U uh
sensing information that is being sent
to us uh by the sensors and also the
predictors that we have in the
perception subsystem so if I may
actually redraw a little bit uh the
problem that we have seen in the kind of
a earlier kind of discussion I have the
environment over here and I do have uh
my perception
block that is actually sending to me uh
predictions about all sorts of things
row sensing information is coming in and
predictions are let's say are coming out
and then I have this
uh system that I'm discussing about the
sort of tracking
uh and uh which will also call
probabilistic reasoning over time and
then I have a
planner and finally I have this kind of
a
actuation or controller if I may call it
like this and uh this is basically uh
what is
been fed back into this environment so
to speak uh that actions are being taken
are causing the change of what we'll be
calling uh the
state so the state is uh uh the uh what
we try to predict it is kept in the
environment and um the evidently the
perception is actually giving us some
information about uh what is there let's
say in terms of location of objects
let's say in the current frame um and uh
in all frames obviously of the video
stream and uh the tracking is uh going
to provide a better uh estimate of this
kind of state to correct for all this
kind of reflexive behavior that we see
inside the perception system uh so I
think it's a good idea to take this term
first this concept of a state and kind
of categorize it and we have plenty of
states in various problems we'll be uh
dealing with in this kind of course so
the first um I will call it um Le level
of a state is the so-call atomic
state so in the atomic State we simply
do not care uh what is this state
consist of um let's say you are um
looking at a uh best path to or best
trajectory to exit a room and uh you
divide the room a floor into cells and
uh that cell um is the the state that
you in right now let's say the location
and how what locations you will occupy
uh to optimally exit the room let's say
in a shortest path or minimum cost um
then in order to solve this problem uh
we do not need to decompose uh that
state of that object or robot uh in any
finer way uh so that is the sort of so
let me write it down uh so planning
problems
uh sometimes use this Atomic kind of
States um and uh in general there will
be solved with uh search based
approaches the second
level and planning is obviously another
uh video uh series of videos that we
will uh sort of see a bit later so the
um second level is the so-called
factored uh States and uh we've been
dealing with Factor States all along so
to give you an idea of a factor State uh
that is a bit outside of the uh space of
computer vision let's take the
description of a kinematic state of a of
a vehicle so I'll be calling uh the
state s let's say from now on and I'll
also be decorating it with subscript T
to indicate that there is some kind of a
time dependency on this state and this
date definitely can be decomposed into
let's say the pose in general the pose
will
be um consist of let's say XYZ
coordinates in the Cartesian kind of
coordinate
system and uh maybe it will be
um associated with also uh three other
variables uh p
r and yo
and then maybe some
velocity uh and some form of let's say
acceleration these are the six socalled
six degrees of
freedom or
dof in general we have an in fact I I
have here also a figure uh in Wikipedia
that kind of explains uh the p is the
pitch the r is the roll and the um Y is
the yo so you have an object in general
which is located let's say here just
like my hand and it has a a pitch it it
can actually has a roll and it can also
has a y in terms of uh you know the
these type of movements to capture all
the potential movements that uh consist
consist that the the pose of an object
consist of okay and then of course you
have some additional ones so that's
basically a simple example of
decomposable state and uh very much we
are in that kind of domain all in our uh
Journey from the perception system until
now and then of course uh at the top of
that you have the so-called um uh
structured
uh where actually I forgot to give an
example
here
perception
localization and uh POS estimation and
so on so another example of let's say
structure state so in that kind of level
we are not really interested to just
capture the state of an object in a
detailed way but we are also interested
to create some kind of global view of
what we have right now so for example
create create some form of
relationships capture relations between
let's say objects and we have of course
uh neural approaches to capture
relationships these are all part of a
bit more advanced discussion on visual
question answering such as relation
networks and other kind of Innovations
in that kind of domain that allow a
differentiable machines to be able to
capture this type of
relationships let's introduce now the
remaining kind of notation and I should
actually point out that uh all of the
treatment over here in this kind of
video um and in this video series on uh
on probabilistic Vision over time is
going to come out of a very important
book um from Sebastian thrun and his
co-authors uh called Pro bistic uh
Robotics and uh this is um I think a a
book that I think you should be in your
bookshelf uh aside from the sort of
books that we have actually recommended
in this kind of course uh because this
will actually open the door to more
advanced topics like simultaneous
localization and mapping extensions to
that on uh you know with visual uh
visual uh slam as we call it uh and but
you know apart from that let's try and
introduce the um what we will be calling
now uh from now on the recursive State
estimator so let me write this
down all
RSC so recursive State estimation
effectively is going to happen over here
in this uh block uh and the state we're
referring to is a state which is
kept in the environment as you know from
the earlier kind of discussions this
state is uh stochastic it's time Ving it
is uh not uh necessarily fully observed
uh from uh from the agent the agent is
actually the whole thing over here uh
and uh the uh uh in in addition to that
is going to be uh uh sort of uh
partially invol partially kind of
estimated from the tracking uh from the
inside this kind of a tracking or
recursive State estimator so tracking
and recursive State estimation is going
to be one and the and and the same thing
um the um State the recursive part is uh
because the um estimation is going to
actually have happen recursively so in
in the steps that we we are now going to
be discussing um now in terms of
notation we are going to have um the
first uh apart from the state s oft I
need a a notation about the action
so so the action is actually uh going to
happen uh as part of this block over
here but uh for our discussion we are
going to be abstracting away all of this
kind of planning let's say trajectory
planning and so on and the various kind
of control subsystem over here and we'll
assume that yes indeed we're taking some
kind of an ction that will involve
potentially some let's say some movement
of the agent in the environment so we
will be denoting with a and with subt u
that kind of action and uh then uh so
and the convention is that uh the
agent
um first takes the action
and
then senses the
environment so the sensing of the
environment for that we will uh not have
another notation so for uh I will call
it the uh measurement we will call it
that
measurement we'll call that as ZT we'll
denote it this as the ZT
and um and of course the measurement as
far as this block is concerned is uh the
uh whatever is comes out of the
perception subsystem okay so I we know
that we have been denoting whatever
prediction we are making um as y hat uh
that is actually coming out of this kind
of block now for this treatment to make
it a bit more compatible with the
literature we changes this y hat to the
um measurement uh ZT but the framew also
accommodates a situation where we don't
have necessarily any processing over
here and we just measure uh with ZT
whatever row sensing information that's
the reason why you actually harmonize uh
both options uh both cases into the same
uh sort of uh variable over here ZT
another convention we will be
adopting uh is that we'll be adopting a
convention that it is uh that say for
actions um is um notational convention
is we will be uh we we will be calling a
of
T1 colum
T2 the sequence of actions that happen
between instances T1 and T2 okay and the
same thing will be um so let me finish
this kind of measurement measurement ZT
uh May
accommodate actually not accommodate but
represent
predictions
from the perception sub
system
subsystem uh or
row
measurements row row sensory information
also generally we will be discussing uh
a sequence of measurements from Z of
from between T1 and and T2 T2 with this
colon kind of notation this col notation
you know originates also from a language
called ma laab from math works and for
those who are working in the robotic
space uh in control theory and things
like that are very familiar with with
that kind of uh tool as it is uh kind of
monopolizing some of the domains over
there okay so so now that we have
introduced if you like these variables
we were definitely going to be
expressing um probability distributions
and we'll be dealing with probability
distributions all along in this
discussion and uh we need to Define uh
some uh assumptions regarding this uh
structure of this probability
distributions but in general uh we will
be discussing a probability uh
distribution that
involves uh the uh State the probability
of being at a state S A Time t uh that
called is called s given um the uh
sequence of previous States let's say
from the beginning of time until T minus
one comma the sequence of actions from
one to T and the sequence of
measurements uh from 1 to T
minus1 okay so this is uh um the this is
going to be the uh
third uh important kind of concept that
we need to introduce here and we will be
calling this this generative model of
State
Evolution uh we will be calling this uh
State transition model
um is
uh
generative generative we call all of
course approaches where we are actually
going to be generating creating this
directly this probability
distribution um so it's a general and of
course this reminds us the discussion we
had also in
classification uh in terms of generative
versus discrimin native kind of uh
classifiers back when we're discussing
this in that kind of video so State
transition model is a
generative um
model for uh the state
Evolution so so the you know the the
important kind of piece to recognize
here is is the following um I'm taking
some measurements I am uh evident
processing them in the perception system
making some kind of predictions where
I'm correcting and tracking uh whatever
is coming out of the perception uh
subsystem I am uh creating if you like
plans based on that information and then
these plans are executed by the
controller who is taking actions it is
going through the these actions are
changing the state of the environment
let's say an an action to move and that
uh change state is being observed Again
by uh via the row sensing measurements
from the perception system and the whole
thing is kind of constantly evolving and
uh this evolution of state is what we
are going to be capturing by the
so-called State transition model how
probabilistically the state will
actually change given previous States
and as you will see a bit um later in
fact right now we'll make an important
assumption regarding the uh completeness
of that state will make this uh what is
called a Arian assumption and now we
will discuss the that kind of assumption
in detail so a
state St is going to be called
complete uh if
uh it is a it is a complete that's why
the name complete is a complete
summary of the
past in other words s of T is a
sufficient
statistic for all past measurements and
actions
so the based on that this this is also
known as uh the
marvian
Assumption and this actually it is that
assumption that actually simplifies
quite a bit a lot of the probability
this conditional probability
distribution we just uh wrote which I'm
going to repeat now so we wrote this s
of T probability distribution of s of T
given the previous uh
States uh the uh
actions up to this moment in time T and
all previous kind of
measurements and this is what allows us
to write it as
follows this assumption P of s of T
given s T minus
one comma a of T and this is a much
simpler um probability distribution uh
that we will definitely are going to
have some uh uh hope that we will be
able to um estimate and um and given
that um uh sort of uh assumption that we
actually made over here I think it's
worthwhile kind of going a little bit
over it so we say that uh obviously the
measurements uh that are uh you know are
not really needed at all because at the
end of the day the only thing that
matters is really the previous state s
of T minus one because the state is
complete and uh uh but the current
action so previous actions are not
needed but definitely out of the all
actions the current action is needed
because it is really the current action
that it used the St the state transition
so let me write it down uh action
at
T
induces the state
transition from St
minus1 to St okay so that's why we have
have to have and uh you know uh
considering that kind of action in other
words then we have this transition okay
the specific action ofd and now we will
need to introduce another U the second
probabilistic model uh the so we we have
going to have two main probabilistic
model what we have to introduce so we
introduce a state transition what causes
the states of course the current action
and uh the simplifying assumption that
allows us to capture that um in uh and
the third and the U sort of second
probabilistic model is going to be
called the
generative model
uh of the
measurements so we have to have a
probability distribution that a model in
other words that will capture those
measurements so again we will making
this uh assumption given the complete
state of the Assumption will make the
following can actually write the
following equation so ZT is now the
random
variable and uh we have uh this
measurement that we are getting a Time T
will depend on U previous uh sequence of
states and actions that we have taken
and also previous measurements from
one t t minus
one and uh this one based on that kind
of assumption can be uh written as P of
ZT given
St and it's actually
also important to just spend a couple of
minutes trying to discuss that kind of
simplification um the fact that I let's
say I'm moving from um I have moved and
I actually have reached this kind of
state let's say next to this kind of
desk um that that state that I am right
now is the only thing that I need to
consider um and the full condition on in
order for me to specify the probability
distribution of let's say how far away
that lets let's say a sensor uh will
bring me on how far away I am from this
kind of obstacle of of the of the wall
or let's say the desk over here so that
is what this probability distribution is
actually capturing uh for example we'll
be assuming in a bit later will be
assuming that this probability
distribution has could be continuous and
it will be um let's say um or discrete
and will take some kind of uh
distribution around it let's say for
continuous will be a gausian
okay and so that is U uh the second kind
of model so we have now two models one
governs the state transition the other
governs the measurements and uh in uh we
we also need to have some uh
representation is not a compulsory thing
to have a representation of the problem
statement in a graphical kind of form
but this has been uh really the norm um
in uh in in this kind of domain to
represent random variabl as nodes and um
with as edges with arrows uh the
transition the evolution of those
probability distributions in fact these
arrows in this case will indicate uh
dependencies okay so um so we will um be
calling this representation the dynamic
Basia
Network it's dynamic because it's going
to be time
varying and basian
because we will be um creating if you
like a filter as we will call it call a
basian kind of filter that it will be
able to give us a good estimates uh of
what we'll be calling now a hidden state
so let me write it
first so in this kind of basian network
which is also known in this case as a
hidden Mark of model
or
hmm we will represent it
as uh the states are represented with
this kind of
circles I'm going to write just three
state St minus
one uh this is obviously my hidden State
I do not know that kind of state it is
that state that it is in that kind of
environment kind of box um and uh that
state
is um dependent
uh from uh the action because the
action will Inu this transition from St
minus one
to um
St okay and then uh we
have evidently we know the action we
will assume that we know the action that
the robot or the agent has actually
taken and in the literature we are
shading this uh whenever you see a
shaded kind of node then um this uh kind
of uh uh node uh is not a random
variable but it is a known uh value it
takes a known value in fact I don't need
this dots because I only going to draw
just three states from St minus1 to St
+1 St + 1
and this is going to be my
um 80 + 1 action and the other node is
uh the
measurements the measurement
node obviously I'm going to be assuming
here that I'm going to be getting some
estimate out of the measurement so some
kind of a row value um from a sensor or
uh from as a predicted value from let's
say let's say an object
detector
ZT and we have ZT +
[Music]
one okay so and this continues into the
future so the arrows of course are the
dependency the measurement I'm getting
evidently is dependent on the state I am
and uh the action and the current state
is is inducing that kind of state
transition okay so we will be um need
now
to Define what we'll be calling some two
key posterior
probabilities uh that represent uh the
state the and this will be called the
beliefs uh two different versions of the
beliefs that we have about where about
we are in terms of State okay so note
that the state is the hidden node a
hidden
variable and that's why the model is
called hidden Markov because we don't
have any dependency from this state uh
other than the previous uh State and the
current
action and that is what was expressed
over here and uh model because evidently
we are dealing with these two
probabilistic models that actually
Define this uh this this this
diagram and um this is also known in the
past as probabilistic graphical models
and we had people have been devising uh
for uh you know a couple of decades now
specific algorithms to uh be able to uh
provide inferences do inferences given
this kind of probabilistic dependencies
between random variables okay so um the
first posterior which I'll be calling
the belief hatut
of St and I'll will symbolize it with
belief of the state St but this hatut
will be mean something is the
probability of s of T given
a so from one to
T
and uh previous measurements
now we will simp simplify this posterior
also uh but
um this belief heart will be uh the
belief will indicate the
belief uh of
being in
state s of
T before
that's the emphasis before taking
measurements before
receiving
measurement
ZT and that's why the index ends at z uh
T minus one okay so this is the belief
and we'll see now the belief C and this
is uh we'll we'll see in a moment how
the two are involved um together how
they we are going to use them um so the
second posterior probability
distribution that I want probability I
want to uh specify is the belief of uh
being in in state
St and uh uh this is uh the the
posterior P of
St given a from one to
T and C from one to T this time
so it's exactly the same thing the
belief
after a receiving
measurement
ZT after receiving measurement R City so
these are the two um I will call it key
uh posteriors that we will uh need to
start finding a way recursive way of
estimating evidently we need this um and
then uh what was going to happen in this
kind of recursion is that if we have
given if you like the diagram if we have
an estimate of um uh the belief of of
this kind of State in an estimate a
posterior probability of being in that
kind of state then we'll be updated
meaning that in the next time uh this
will actually be um used next time to
come with an estimate of this posterior
at T +1 now we'll need to see how this
is going to be done